Finding Aid for Child and Family Life Department (University of Michigan) records, 1922-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Child and Family Life Department (University of Michigan) records 1922-2001, 1922-1960
University of Michigan. Child and Family Life Department.
2 oversize boxes
7 linear feet
0501 Bimu 2
The Child and Family Life Department, successor unit to the University Hospital School established in 1922, has provided educational and social support for sick and disabled children while hospitalized at the University of Michigan. The record group includes annual reports, histories, correspondence, and other administrative records relating to the operation of the school. The bulk of the record group is the visual materials series, including photographs, negatives, slides, films, and scrapbooks showing educational techniques, health care treatment, and hospitalized children.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Records were received from the Child and Family Life Department in December 2003 (Donor # 9411 ).
The Child and Family Life Department records are open for research use with the exception of patient files which are restricted for 100 years from date of creation. The restricted files have been removed to the Bentley Library vault.
The following are terms of restrictions for specific genres of records found in this record group:
patient/client records are restricted for one-hundred years from date of creation.
The record group University of Michigan Child and Family Department contains restricted files; these files have been removed to the vault.
The Hospital School (now known as the Child and Family Life Department) has since 1922 provided support for sick and disabled children to continue their education and growth during extended stays within a hospital setting. At their September 1922 meeting, the University of Michigan Board of Regents accepted the contribution of $1500 from the King’s Daughters of Michigan to pay the annual salary of a teacher for the sick and crippled in the University Hospital, beginning the Hospital School program. Miss Ruby Carlton served as the first paid staff member of the University Hospital School, with school rooms located in the Main Hospital (for cases of acute illness) and in the South Department, where convalescent cases resided. While intended to serve children between the ages of 7 and 15, in the early years of the school, staff also instructed older patients as well as patients boarded out by the hospital.
The Hospital School was situated within the Social Services Department, which also consisted of departments for Case Work, Occupational Therapy, Special Activity, and Library. Dorothy Ketcham, Director of the Social Services Department in 1922, is largely credited with garnering the support of the hospital administration and the School of Education for the establishment of the Hospital School program. Ketcham described the purpose of the school in her volume One Hundred Thousand Days of Illness as “to assure the child and adult healthy minds while developing vigorous bodies. Our approach has always been to help the patient maintain normality, providing social experiences to safeguard this growth process” (xiii).
In her first year of work, Carlton supervised some 30 volunteer student teachers, one student for credit, ten volunteer storytellers (largely from the Department of Public Speaking), eight volunteer Binet testers (from the School of Education’s advanced course in mental testing) and one part-time teacher, Winifred Milor, who served for two months over the summer. Pupils numbered 324 in the first year, while the length of attendance ranged from as little as one week to the entire year. Daily instruction time was limited to between one and two hours, due to limited staffing.
The Crippled Children’s Act of 1927 allowed for financing the bedside teaching of crippled children through the provision of state funds for curriculum, texts, personnel and methods approved by the Superintendent of Public Instruction. To meet the requirements for funding, the Hospital School established a relationship for supervision by the University of Michigan School of Education. Children from the Michigan Children’s Institute (MCI) began attending the Hospital School’s courses in 1939, with responsibility for MCI transferred away from the Hospital School during the 1950s. The 1956-1957 Annual Report indicates that plans were in the works for the establishment of a program for these children in either the Ann Arbor Public Schools or by the hiring of their own teacher on a full-time basis.
Outside financial support has been key to the functioning of the program over the years, with the King’s Daughters and Kiwanis clubs contributing funds for many projects, including a recreation room and gifts for the annual Christmas celebrations. Beginning in 1928, the Galens Honorary Medical Society raised and provided funds for the establishment of an arts and crafts program within the hospital. This included a fully functional workshop where looms, sewing machines, a jigsaw, and carpenter’s benches, amongst other tools, were available.
With a philosophy of treating the entire patient, the Hospital School program has been home to a Boy Scout troop in the 1920s and 1930s, a number of resident animals, including two “honey bears” in the 1950s, arts and crafts programs, vocational training, citizenship training, and an annual holiday celebration, amongst a plethora of recreation and educational programs. The Hospital School program was featured in a Life magazine article in 1956.
Following the opening of the C.S. Mott Children’s Hospital in 1969, the Hospital School relocated from “Old Main” where it had resided since its establishment. The space in Mott included six multi-purpose rooms, and a large activity center on the top floor. The activity center contained an arts and crafts area, children’s library, kitchen, outdoor playground, and administrative offices.
The move to Mott also prompted the first of several reorganizations of the Hospital School and Activity Program. Despite several name changes, the mission remains largely the same as that of the Hospital School established in the 1920s. With a staff that includes recreational therapists, activities therapists, child life specialists, an art therapist, and a music-and-health consultant, as well as an active volunteer population, the program continues to provide hospitalized children the support and opportunity to grow and learn.
In 1985 the name was changed to the Child Life Department to reflect the growing emphasis on meeting the psychosocial aspects of hospitalization. In 1999 the title was expanded to Child and Family Life.
For additional information about the Hospital School, the researcher may wish to consult:
The University of Michigan: An Encyclopedic Survey, pages 990-992, which includes a description of the Social Services Department, the Hospital School, and the Occupational Therapy Department.
One Hundred Thousand Days of Illness by Dorothy Ketcham. (Ann Arbor, MI: Edwards Brothers, Inc., 1939).
The Child and Family Life Department records relate mainly to the operation of the Hospital School, and include reports, minutes, correspondence, and a wide variety of visual materials, including photographs, slides, negatives, and films documenting the programming efforts of the staff and the experiences of its patients. The evolution of educational philosophy and changes in hospitalization and treatment can be seen both in the documentation as well as through the images that are included in the record group. The records (7 linear feet, 2 oversize boxes) date from 1922 to 2001, but primarily document the period from 1922 to 1960. The records are organized in three series: Reports and Histories, Correspondence, and Visual Materials.
Subjects:
Children's literature--Bibliography--Yearbooks.
Contributors:
Child Study Association of America. Children's Book Committee.; Child Study Association of America. Book Review Committee.
- Reports and Histories 1922-1969
  The series Reports and Histories, 1922-1969 (2.5. linear feet) is alphabetically arranged and contains annual reports of the Hospital School as a unit, scattered annual reports for its subunits, and reports made to external agencies, including the Kiwanis (a funder) and the Michigan Children’s Institute, which sent some children to the Hospital School for classes. Reports and articles written by staff members provide insight into the educational philosophy and goals of the Hospital School, and various histories provide basic background on the program.
  - Achievement Tests, Summaries of Treatments
    [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2039, removed to vault storage]
  - "Analytical Study," 1938 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports
    - Hospital School
      - 1923-1950, 1953-1957, 1960-1962, 1964-1969, 15 folders (Box 1)
    - Kiwanis (Box 2)
      - 1928-1933 1935-1947 1949, 5 folders (Box 2)
    - Michigan Children's Institute (MCI)
      - 1945, 1948, 1949 (Box 2)
    - Neuropsychiatric Institute (NPI)
      - 1949 (Box 2)
    - Social Service Department
      - 1926 (Box 2)
    - Special Education Department
      - 1930-1944 1946, 8 folders (Box 2)
  - Articles by Staff Members about Hospital School 1928-1948, 1956 (Box 2)
  - Christmas 1947-1950 (Box 2)
  - Christmas Committee 1949-1950 (Box 2)
  - Commencement Program (photocopy) 1930 (Box 2)
  - Daily Schedule 1941 (Box 2)
  - Diploma (Box 2)
  - Histories (Box 3)
    - Child Life Department History and Program Information (Box 3)
    - Galens Shop Program History (Box 3)
    - Hospital School and Activity Program History (Box 3)
  - Holiday Cards (Box 3)
  - Lectures, Curricula, Unidentified Reports 1923-1940, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Marie Mickle (Volunteer) (Box 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box 3)
  - Pediatric Bone Marrow Transplantation Patient Handbook, ca. 1980 (Box 3)
  - Reports
    - Academic Training in University of Michigan Hospital School (C.L. Matheison) 1932 (Box 3)
    - American Sociological Society Census of Current Research Projects 1938 (Box 3)
    - Going to School in a Hospital, undated. (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous Statistical Reports 1942-1947 (Box 3)
  - Social Service Department Planning Group Minutes 1949-1950 (Box 3)
  - Teacher Information (Box 3)
  - Volunteer Orientation Training Information, ca. 1990s (Box 3)
  - Appropriations and Budget 1928-1949 (scattered) (Box 3)
  - Development of Program in Special Education for Teachers of Hospital Children 1946-1951 (Box 3)
  - Hospital Schools and Education of Crippled Children in Other States 1942 (Box 3)
  - King's Daughters 1922-1948 (scattered) (Box 3)
  - Kiwanis Recreation Program 1926-1929 (Box 3)
  - Michigan Children's Institute 1941-1944 (Box 3)
  - Michigan Crippled Children's Commission 1927-1947, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1928-1953 (Box 3)
  - School of Education and Office of the Superintendent of Public Instruction 1922-1949 (Box 3)
  - University Hospital 1940-1946 (Box 3)
  - Veterans Receiving Center Students 1949-1950 (Box 3)
- Visual Materials 1922-2001
  The series Visual Materials, 1922-2001 (4 linear feet, and 2 oversize boxes) is arranged by format and topic, and includes negatives, photographs, slides, motion pictures, and scrapbooks. While the bulk of these materials are unidentified and undated, they nevertheless provide a vivid portrait of the Hospital School experience and the teaching methods and activity programs. In particular, the researcher can see visual examples of arrangements made for bedside teaching and activities, educational activities and methods, annual Christmas parties, the Polio Ward in 1953, general hospital practices, and numerous images of hospitalized children. The images are of excellent quality, document some campus locations which are no longer extant (such as facilities in “Old Main” Hospital), and make a powerful visual statement about the status of health care and treatment over the years as well the dedication and positive outlook of both staff and patients in overcoming the physical barriers to learning. The images have value for those interested in learning about hospital school settings, but also to those interested in learning about the evolution of treatment and health care, at both the local and national level. Many of the topical categories were those assigned by the creating unit, and there are some overlaps between topics such that the researcher would be well-served to look at a number of topics for relevant images.
  - Photographs
    - Chronological
      - circa 1920s (Box 4)
      - Scrapbook circa 1920s (Box 4)
      - 1929 (First Graduating Class) (Box 4)
      - 1935 (Box 4)
      - 1936 (Box 4)
      - 1937 (Box 4)
      - 1957-1961 (Box 4)
      - 1962-1963 (Box 4)
      - 1966 (includes negatives) (Box 4)
      - 1969 (Box 4)
      - 1972 (Includes 50th anniversary) (Box 4)
      - 1986-1987 (Box 4)
      - 1995 (Mott Seurat) (Box 4)
      - 2001 (Box 4)
    - Topical
      - Animals (Box 4)
      - Arts and Crafts (Box 4)
      - Basket Weaving and Weaving (Box 4)
      - Bedside Teaching (Box 4)
      - Buildings (Box 4)
      - Burn Unit/Isolation (Box 4)
      - Christmas, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - C.P.H. (Box 4)
      - Emmett Kelley visit 1966 (includes negatives) (Box 4)
      - Galens Poster Children (Box 4)
      - Galens Tag Day (Box 4)
      - Galens Woodshop (Box 4)
      - Graduates 1938 (Box 4)
      - King's Daughters (Box 4)
      - Kiwanis (Box 4)
      - Kiwanis Open House 1991 (Box 4)
      - Life Magazine Photographs, 1956 (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous oversize photos
        - Miscellaneous Images of Hospital School (Box 8)
        - Scrapbook 1960s (Box 8)
        - Miscellaneous Images, including surgery, doctors, nurses, and pediatric patients (Box 9)
      - Miscellaneous Bulletin Boards and Displays (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous Visitors (Including Hillary Clinton and Tom Monaghan) (Box 5)
      - Music (Box 5)
      - Parties (Box 5)
      - Picnics (Box 5)
      - Plaques at Mott Hospital (Box 5)
      - Play, 3 folders (Box 5)
      - Polio Ward 1953, undated (Box 5)
      - Porch Area (Box 5)
      - Portraits (Box 5)
      - Preschool (Box 5)
      - Primary Students (Box 5)
      - Recreation Department (Box 5)
      - School in 10W (Box 5)
      - Secondary Students (Box 5)
      - Staff (includes negatives) (Box 5)
      - Treating Patients (Box 5)
  - Lantern Slides, 1 envelopes (Box 5)
  - Negatives
    - Chronological
      - 1962 (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous circa 1969 (Box 5)
    - Topical
      - Animals (Box 5)
      - Cherry Pie Baking (Box 5)
      - Christmas (Box 6)
      - Easter (Box 6)
      - Forney Clement Memorial Foundation (Box 6)
      - Fun (Box 6)
      - Galens Drive (Shots for use in the drive, not of the drive itself) (Box 6)
      - Galens Poster (Box 6)
      - Galens Shop (Box 6)
      - General Electric Christmas Gifts for 13th Floor (Box 6)
        (Includes Print)
      - Halloween (Box 6)
      - Hawaiian Party (Box 6)
      - Ice Cream (Box 6)
      - Kiwanis Poster Images (Box 6)
      - Michigan Children's Institute 1951 (Box 6)
      - Miscellaneous School Shots (Box 6)
      - Neuropsychiatric Institute (Box 6)
      - Nursery (Box 6)
      - Parties (Box 6)
      - Portraits, Staff and Kids (Box 6)
      - Program Negatives (AACCH-1969) (Box 6)
      - Puppet Show (Box 6)
      - Roof (Box 6)
      - 6W Shop (Box 6)
      - 6W Ward (Box 6)
      - Teaching Unit on Bees (Box 6)
      - Teenagers (Box 6)
      - Use of the Ceiling Projector (Box 6)
      - Volunteers (Box 6)
  - Slides
    - Child Life Department Presentation and Narrative 1988 (Box 6)
    - Kiwanis Fund Raising Presentation and Audio Cassette 1992 (Box 6)
    - Mott Volunteers in Action Presentations 1975 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous Dated 1958-1992, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous Undated (Box 6)
  - Films
    - Motion Pictures (16 mm)
      - Christmas 1927 (Box 7)
      - "Cycle of Care" (Box 7)
      - "Education Program of the Galen Shop" (Box 7)
      - "Education Through Play"
        - Color (21P) (Box 7)
        - Color, Sound (3306) (Box 7)
        - Silent Kodachrome (3920) (Box 7)
      - Hospital #1 (Shot Inside Hospital) (Box 7)
      - Kiwanis 1935 (Box 7)
      - "Trip to the Hospital" (Box 7)
    - U-Matic Videotapes
      - "Leonard Z. Lion Presents: Learning About Your Operation" (Box 7)
      - Mott Slides (Box 7)
      - WDIV-TV Segment Detroit Today, Mott Hospital School, March 22, 1981 (Box 7)
    - VHS Videotapes
      - Hillary Rodham Clinton's Visit January 17, 1996 (Box 7)